Register of the Ethan Theodore Colton papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ethan Theodore Colton papers
1917-1952,
1918-1935
XX380
Colton, Ethan Theodore, 1872-
9 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 3.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, writings, translations, and clippings, relating to European Student Relief activities in Russia and other European countries, 1920-1925; and to social conditions, the educational system, and the status of religion in Russia in the 1920s and 1930s. Includes the memoirs of E. T. Colton and 13 anti-religious Soviet posters. All material is from 1917-1935, except for Colton's 1952 memoirs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Darius Alton Davis papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Russell McCulloch Story Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
American Relief Administration. European Operations Records, Hoover Institution Archives
American Relief Administration. Russian Operations Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Young Men's Christian Associations Collection, Hoover Institution Archives
American National Red Cross records, Hoover Institution Archives
Roy Ross Clark papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1872 Born, Palmyra, Jefferson County, Wisconsin
1892 Enters Dakota Wesleyan University, Mitchell, South Dakota; becomes active in campus YMCA and Mitchell Epworth League
1898 Graduates from Dakota Wesleyan University, Mitchell, South Dakota
1899-1904 Staff member with Student Young Men's Christian Associations (YMCA)
1904-1917 Works for YMCA to build local Associations' support for YMCA World Service
1918-1924 Administers European Student Relief (ESR) aid services in Russia and Siberia and to Russian émigrés in Europe; serves as YMCA liaison to American Relief Administration (ARA)
1921 April ESR conference at Turnov, Czechoslovakia
1922 Arrives back in New York from field work in Europe
by 1923 to at least 1924 Works from Student Friendship office, 341 Madison Avenue, New York, NY
1923 ARA programs conclude
1925 ESR programs conclude (See Box 6)
1925-1932 Executive secretary, YMCA World Services
by 1925 to at least 1932 YMCA Press correspondence is directed to Colton at 341 Madison Avenue, New York, NY
1929 LL.D. degree
by 1931 Resident of Upper Montclair, New Jersey
1931 Author of The X Y Z of Communism (New York, Macmillan Company), a response to Bukarin and Preobrazhensky's The A B C of Communism (1921)
1932 Retires from YMCA World Services executive secretary position at age 60, per YMCA requirement; continues YMCA committee work
1932-1942 Annual lecture tours, writes books
1935 Author of Four Patterns of Revolution; Communist U.S.S.R., Fascist Italy, Nazi Germany, New Deal America (New York, [YMCA] Association Press)
1940 Author of Forty Years with Russians (New York, Association Press), forward by John R. Mott
1943-1946 Executive director, YMCA War Prisoners? Aid Services in United States
1944 Author of Toward the Understanding of Europe (New York, Association Press)
1952 Author of Memoirs of Ethan T. Colton, Sr., 1872-1952, self-published
1953 Author of The Russia We Face Now (Washington, D.C.: The Public Affairs Institute)
Historical Note
The European Student Relief program (ESR) was instituted in 1918 as a complement to the US-government-funded American Relief Administration (ARA) program, to provide European students, and later professors and technical workers, with food, clothing, and shoes, and sometimes medical services, tuition aid, and textbooks, and other support for intellectual work. ESR relief work pursued a limited scope, focusing on university-affiliated populations to support the reconstruction of war-torn Europe, and to build goodwill between students in Europe and the U.S.
Colton's papers reflect the complicated organizational relationships in the administration of the American Section of ESR (also known as ASESR). According to histories of the YMCA, the European Student Relief program was inaugurated by the World's Student Christian Federation (WSCF), a Geneva-based organization founded in 1895 as a trans-national complement to the YMCA. WSCF founding general secretary John R. Mott served as general secretary throughout the ESR period, while simultaneously serving as the general secretary of the YMCA from 1915-1928, and from 1926-1937 as president of the YMCA's World Committee and the general secretary of President Wilson's National War Work Council. While ESR was a program of the WSCF, in the public ESR was frequently conflated with the ARA, and in ESR reports Colton is sometimes identified as a member of the staff of ARA Director General Colonel Haskell.
Documents in Colton's papers describe ESR's mission, organizational structure, personnel, and mode of operation (Box 2), and note a Russian expulsion of the YMCA in 1918 (Box 1).
In supporting ESR work to build goodwill between students in the United States and war-torn Europe, the WSCF created a Student Friendship Fund (SFF), which conducted publicity and fundraising work in the US, provided grassroots fundraising strategies and materials to college students and Christian youth organizations, and collected donations of cash as well as second-hand clothing and shoes for ESR to distribute in Europe.
References:
Colton, Ethan Theodore, Forty Years with Russians, New York, Association Press, 1940; especially pages 128, 132, and 161 on YMCA Press
Hopkins, C. Howard, History of the Y. M. C. A. in North America, New York: Association Press, 1951; especially page 687
Nobel Foundation, "John R. Mott: The Nobel Peace Prize 1946," "Biography" and "Presentation Speech," 1946, [viewed 2010 January 26] http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1946/mott-bio.html; http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1946/press.html
Rouse, Ruth, The World's Student Christian Federation: A History of the First Thirty Years, London: S. C. M. Press Ltd., 1948, especially pages 55, 79
Shedd, Clarence P., Two Centuries of Student Christian Movements: Their Origin and Intercollegiate Life, New York: Association Press, 1934
Shedd, Clarence Prouty, "and other contributors," History of the World's Alliance of Young Men's Christian Associations, London: S.P.C.K., for the World's Committee of Young Men's Christian Associations, 1955; especially pages 355-6, 353, 472, 565, 674, 701
Stuer, Kenneth, "'For the Millions of Men Now Under Arms': American YMCA Prisoner-of-War Diplomacy in Western Europe," chapter 4 of Pursuit of an 'Unparalleled Opportunity,' New York: Columbia University Press, 2008, [viewed 2010 January 12] http://www.gutenberg-e.org/steuer/
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ethan T. Colton papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist of correspondence, reports, writings, translations, and clippings, relating to European Student Relief activities in Russia and other European countries, 1920-1925; and to social conditions, the educational system, and the status of religion in Russia in the 1920s and 1930s. Includes the memoirs of E. T. Colton and 13 anti-religious Soviet posters. Except for Colton's 1952 memoirs, all material is from 1917 to 1935.
Colton spent his whole career with the Young Men's Christian Association. His early work to build local Associations' support for the YMCA's World Service, or Overseas Division, was followed by his assignment to executive administration of the European Student Relief program.
Colton's papers offer particularly vivid qualitative and quantitative data on conditions for civilians in university areas throughout Europe following World War I, and U.S. and international food and clothing aid. The ESR reports were often in the form of letters from ESR staff, and are rich with first-person accounts of conditions aid workers found in recipient countries throughout Europe after World War I, and particularly Russia and Siberia in the wake of the Russian Civil War and subsequent famine in Russia.
The documents exhibit the range of data and synthesis required for administering a large aid operation, assessing needs and program effectiveness, and conducting publicity and securing donations to sustain or expand and improve the relief efforts. The material also provides perspective on transition of government-administered operations to private non-governmental organizations.
After the ESR program concluded in 1925, Colton continued with YMCA Overseas work on behalf of Russian émigrés, and maintained a focus on Russia and communism. Colton's papers reflect his collecting data, writing, and speaking about the practical impacts of Soviet government policies; communist outreach to youth; the relation of communism to religion; the Russian Orthodox Church, and Russian Orthodox religious figures under Soviet rule and official atheism. Some ESR reports and correspondence bear annotations related to this later work.
Except for Colton's memoirs, his papers at the Hoover Institution Archives contain no material related to his post-retirement reactivation as executive director of the YMCA War Prisoners' Aid Services in the United States during World War II.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
European Student Relief.; Student Friendship Fund.; Young Men's Christian associations.; Education Soviet Union.; International relief.; Soviet Union--History Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.; Soviet Union--Religion.; Soviet Union--Social conditions.; World War, 1914-1918--Refugees.; World War, 1914-1918--Europe.
Collection Contents
- Memoir, circa 1952 (Box 1)
  Covers his origins to his professional life through 1952, with some information about his wife and children
  - Memoirs of Ethan T. Colton, Sr., 1872-1952, self-published, circa 1952 (Folder 1: 1)
- Working documents, 1918-1932, undated (Box 1, 10)
  Consists of writings, notes for speeches, and selected documents from ESR work and the YMCA Press Russian news translations, relating to themes Colton would draw on throughout his career: analysis of the Soviet government's policies and effects related to daily life and religion, and the potential transformative effects of Christian Internationalism, especially as a potential counterpoint to Communist Internationalism. Materials for an exhibit on the Soviet Union include photos and Soviet propaganda posters, 1919-1931, reprinted with English translations and annotations. Related: Subject Files, 1918-1934 and undated, and European Student Relief reports, 1920-1925
  - Writings, 1930s (Folder 1)
    - Drafts for The X Y Z of Communism (1931), probably 1930 (Folder 1:2)
  - Writings, probably 1930 (Folder 1)
    - Drafts for The X Y Z of Communism (1931), probably 1930 (Folder 1:2)
  - Exhibit on Soviet Union, probably early 1930s (Folder 1, 10)
    - Soviet propaganda poster reprints with English translations and annotations, probably early 1930s (Folder 10:1)
      Dates of original posters range from 1929-1931
    - Russian poster, 1921 (Folder 10:2)
      Mining industry
    - Printed materials, 1932, undated (Folder 1:3)
    - ESR aid work photos, Kiev and Ekaterinoslav, 1924, undated (Folder 1:4)
  - Working Documents, 1918-1932, undated (Folder 1)
    - Working Documents, 1920-1932, undated, (bulk 1925-1932) (Folder 1:5)
      Includes writings by Colton and typescript notes, including for speeches, mainly relating to the Soviet Union and Christianity throughout the world
    - Working Documents, USSR and religion, 1923-1932, undated (Folder 1:6-7)
      Includes writings, ESR correspondence, reports, translations of Russian newspaper articles, and clippings, related to the Russian Orthodox Church, Christian student and evangelical movements in the USSR, the YMCA, and Soviet and Communist positions on these groups
    - Working Documents, Russia and religion, 1918-1922, undated (Folder 1:8)
      Includes memoranda, writings, and clippings related to the Patriarch Tikhon and the Russian Orthodox church, and the withdrawal of the YMCA from Russia. Also includes typescript translations of Russian news articles, and speech by Trotsky concerning the ARA
    - Working Documents, Russia and Soviet Union, 1922-1932 (Folder 1:9-11)
      Includes ESR reports and correspondence, including holographic reports and testimonials from relief recipients at a Moscow university scientific organization. Clippings and printed material include map of YMCA centers in Europe and Siberia, 1920
- European Student Relief reports, 1920-1925 (Box 2-6)
  Contains reports and correspondence related to the deployment of aid, assessing program success, and gathering testimonials and other evidence in support of continuing aid. Includes many file copies of third-party correspondence with Edgar MacNaughton, the ASESR Director for Kiev. Also includes reports of manifestations of anti-Semitic sentiments in Europe, and other trends in ethnic relations that might impact ESR work, such as relating to Armenian refugees in Poland. Includes thank-you letters from individual and organizational recipients of ESR aid in Russia and Germany. Related: Student Friendship files, 1921-1922; Subject Files, 1917-1934, undated; Incremental materials, October 1987
  - Europe, general, 1921-1923 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes administrative memoranda regarding operations and relations of ESR to WSCF and the YMCA, and reports of conditions and ESR work across Europe, including from SFF conference
  - Europe, general, 1921-1923 (Folder 2: 2)
    Includes reports related to conditions at European universities and hospitals, and fundraising strategies for YMCAs. Also includes letter from the first Indian YMCA Secretary in India regarding aid to Viennese students
  - Europe, general, 1921 June 1 (Folder 2: 3)
    Annual report
  - Europe, general, 1921-1923 (Folder 2: 4)
    Includes report from a Federation Conference, possibly of the YMCA, held at Tsing Hua College, Peking (Beijing); and chart of contributions and distributions of the ESR and ARA, 1920-1921
  - Europe, general, 1921-1925 (bulk 1924-1925) (Folder 2: 5-6)
    Includes reports, translations of newspaper articles, and copies of correspondence, including from university organizations, largely related to aid to professors and scientific workers, and to fundraising. Also includes reports related to the Leningrad flood of 1924
  - Europe, general, 1924-1925 (Folder 2: 7)
    Includes letters from MacNaughton to Colton, and typescript copies of MacNaughton's numbered dispatches
  - Europe, general, 1923-1925 (bulk 1924-1925) (Folder 2: 8)
  - Austria, 1920-1921 (Folder 2: 9-10)
  - Austria, 1921-1922 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Austria, Vienna, 1920-1922 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Bulgaria, 1922-1923 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1920-1922 (Folder 3: 2)
    Exhibit A - Exhibit L. Includes reports on relief work for refugee students, case study of a Russian student, and samples of application documents required for relief and for free tuition
  - Czechoslovakia, 1920-1922 (Folder 3: 3)
    Exhibit G photographs. Six composed photographs depicting ESR self-help workshops in Prague. Scene include students washing and mending donated second-hand clothes, and shoemakers making repairs.
  - Czechoslovakia, 1920-1923 (Folder 3: 4-5)
    Includes list of ESR delegates, by country, to ESR conference in Turnov, Czechoslovakia, 1922 April 8-15
  - Denmark, 1921-1922 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Estonia, 1922 (Folder 3: 7)
  - France, 1922-1923 (Folder 3: 8)
    In English, French, and German
  - Germany, 1921-1923 (Folder 3: 9-11)
  - Germany, 1920-1922 (Folder 3: 12-14)
  - Holland, 1921-1922 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Hungary, 1920-1923 (Folder 3: 16-17)
    Includes correspondence reporting Christian persecution of Jews in Hungary, and discussing consequences for conducting European Student Relief
  - Yugoslavia, 1922-1923 (Folder 3: 18)
    Includes reports on Belgrade and Zagreb, Yugoslavia
  - Latvia, 1921-1922 (Folder 3: 19)
    Includes reports on Riga as well as on Lithuania and Estonia
  - Near East, 1921-1923 (Folder 4: 1)
    Includes reports on work in Greece, mainly Athens, Constantinople, and Smyrna; and Turkey, with one report on Turnov, Czechoslovakia
  - Norway, 1921 April (Folder 4: 2)
  - Poland, 1921-1923 (Folder 4: 3-4)
    Includes reports on relief work, sample registration documents for applicants, and samples of a special fundraising certificate and stamps. Some items hand-annotated Exhibit I through Exhibit VII
  - Romania, 1922-1923 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Russia, 1921-1923 (Folder 4: 6)
    Includes reports on conditions and work in Bratislava, Kazan, Moscow, Odessa, and Petrograd, as well as Krakow, Poland, and the Ukraine; transcriptions of appeals for support by prominent figures including Samuel Gompers, Maksim Gorky; and annual report of the Kiev Students' Christian Association
  - Russia, 1922-1923 (Folder 4: 7-9)
    Includes reports on conditions and work in Ekaterinoslav, Kazan, Kiev, Moscow, Riga, Samara, and Saratov; to Russian refugee students in Belgrade; and Czechoslovakian aid to Ukrainians and Russians. Also includes reports and memoranda regarding Communist policies on religion, and development of ESR policy regarding students posting notices in ESR dining halls
  - Russia, 1921-1923 (bulk 1922-1923) (Folder 4: 10)
    Includes reports on conditions and work in Ekaterinoslav, Moscow, Odessa, Penza, Petrograd, Rostov, Saratov, Simbirsk, Tomsk; and Kharkov and Simferopol, Ukraine. Also includes Ukrainian student association statement
  - Russia, 1922-1923 (Folder 5: 1)
    Includes reports on conditions and ARA and ESR work; including regarding administration and prospects for continuance
  - Russia, 1923-1924 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Russia, 1921-1925 (bulk 1923-1925) (Folder 5: 3-7)
    Includes letters from MacNaughton
  - Serbia, 1922-1923 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Sweden, 1921 May (Folder 5: 9)
  - Switzerland, 1920-1921 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Ukraine, Kiev, 1924 (Folder 5: 11)
    Includes report from MacNaughton, and reports of Dr. S. L. Malinovskii, Chief of Medical Staff, Kiev
  - ESR recipient thank-you letters, Russia and Germany, 1924 (Folder 5: 12)
    Related: Russia, 1921-1923
- Student Friendship Fund files, 1921-1922 (Box 5-6)
  Consists of solicitation strategies, fundraising materials distributed, and sample press releases with tracking of distribution and stories placed. Related: European Student Relief reports, 1920-1925; Subject files, Relief, Russia, 1923-1924, and Relief, 1922-1926 (bulk 1924-1925)
  - Student Friendship Fund fundraising materials distributed, 1921-1922 (Folder 5: 13-14)
  - Student Friendship Fund fundraising materials distributed, 1921-1922 (Folder 6: 1-2)
  - Student Friendship Fund press releases, 1921-1922 (Folder 6: 3)
    Consists of samples of stories sent to newspapers, college papers, and religious papers, with recording of distribution and results
- Subject files, 1917-1934, undated (Box 6-8, 10)
  Includes many ESR reports, typescript translations of Russian news articles, newspaper clippings, and other printed materials, largely related to Russia; the Soviet government; data about the need for aid such as ESR relief; the impacts of communism and goals for communist expansion, particularly among the youth; and the current state of and prospects for religion in the Soviet Union. Includes assessments of the late phase of ESR aid, and suggestions for continuance, perhaps by successor organizations. Also includes documents relating to the YMCA's mission for and accomplishments of work in Russia and the Soviet Union
  - Unidentified, "Memorandum Concerning Russia,", after 1927 (Folder 6: 4)
    Margin notes by Colton
  - Chamberlin, W.H., 1925-1931, undated (Folder 6: 5)
    Clippings of the Moscow correspondent's reporting for the Christian Science Monitor
  - Duranty, Walter, 1925-1932 (bulk 1931-1932) (Folder 6: 6)
    Clippings of Duranty's reporting on the Soviet Union for the New York Times
  - Europe, 1931, undated (Folder 6: 7)
    Consists of ARA Association Review clippings and a 1931 League of Nations publication on armaments and the USSR
  - Relief, Russia, 1923-1924 (Folder 6: 8)
    Consists mainly of ESR reports on food and clothing aid, aid to professors and scientific workers, and subsidies to create two medical journals in Ekaterinoslav. Includes program evaluation reports, and photos
  - Relief, 1922-1926 (bulk 1924-1925) (Folder 6: 9-14)
    Includes ESR reports related to libraries, textbooks, and dispensaries, and proposals for continuance of ESR aid, or aid by successor organization. Also includes SFF fundraising materials
  - Russia, 1924-1926 (Folder 6: 15-16)
    Includes reports related to physical education and to Christianity. Also includes typescript translations from Izvestia, and periodical articles on Communism in English and German with English translation
  - Russia - class war, 1919-1931, undated (bulk 1930-1931) (Folder 6: 17)
  - Russia - economics, 1924-1932, undated (bulk 1931-1932) (Folder 6: 18)
    Includes holographic notes, possibly for a speech by Colton
  - Russia - education, 1924-1932, undated (Folder 7: 1)
  - Russia - foreign affairs, 1918-1932 (bulk 1930-1932) (Folder 7: 2)
    Includes typescript translations of Russian and French newspaper articles and letters
  - Russia - labor, 1925-1932, undated (Folder 7: 3)
  - Russia - militarism, 1923 and probably 1932 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Russia - party affairs, 1925-1932 (Folder 7: 5)
    Lenin-Stalin government
  - Russia - recognition, 1924-1926, undated (Folder 7: 6)
  - Russia - religion, 1917-1931, undated (bulk 1924-1930) (Folder 7: 7-10)
    Includes writings by Colton, and documents related to the mission and governance of the YMCA's religious services for Russians. Also includes reports and correspondence related to the status of churches, chapels, synagogues, religious practitioners, Russian religious figures, the Bibles for Russia program and the All-Russian Evangelical Christian Union
  - Russia - rural, 1924-1932, undated. (Folder 7: 11)
    Includes copy of letter from Sherwood Eddy, 1929
  - Russia - social welfare, 1931-1932 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Russia - youth, 1927-1932 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Soviet Russia - nature and theory, 1932, undated (Folder 7: 14)
    Consists of periodical clippings and a typescript translation of Russian newspaper item, 1932
  - Third International, 1928-1932, undated (Folder 7: 15-16)
    Includes typescript reports assessing number of communist organizations for children internationally, and communist press for children throughout Europe. Also includes typescript translations related to the YMCA and Communism in China, 1927; and American Vigilant Intelligence Federation, "The Economic Situation of the Soviet Union," 1932, typescript report
  - Third International, 1928-1932, undated (Folder 10)
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation, Bolshevist Organizations in the United States of America at Present Time, 1931 (Folder 10: 3)
      Poster